<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-24T08:59:28+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Oykun Yilmaz</title><subtitle>Designer based in London.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Letter to Young Designers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/letter-to-young-designers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter to Young Designers" /><published>2024-04-28T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/letter-to-young-designers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/letter-to-young-designers.html">&lt;p&gt;Dear Young Designer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can already call yourself a &quot;Designer&quot;. Everybody in this world is a designer. What you want to be is an &quot;Excellent Designer&quot;. To become that;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explore! Do not worry about specialising. You will have time for that. Take whatever comes your path in design. Find out what you are good at, what you are terrible at, what you enjoy/hate doing... You will discover who you are and what you have to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you explore, build lifelong relationships with people. Make friends with clients, Care for them, care for their business, You will never be alone in your life-long journey with design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&apos;t be lazy! Don&apos;t sit around and wait for people to give you work. Do not be satisfied with the bare minimum to save the day. Go above and beyond. Show what you can do, first to yourself! Make the most of the opportunities you have for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move your head out of your screen! The answer to being an exceptional designer is not all in the pixels you move around. It&apos;s rather in the world out there. Go out, see a musical, get lost in a museum, try surfing, try new things. As you expand your experiences, you will notice the way you see design will evolve for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read! Not as in moving your eyes over the letters, but looking through them. Study them! Not only design books but philosophy, architecture, science, history, fiction, nonfiction... Expand your mind&apos;s horizon. Design is everywhere, fed by everything. Read them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&apos;t worry about good design when you first start! Just design! Accumulate as many ideas, techniques, styles, approaches, art movements as you can. Your creativity will harmonise them with your self-being. It will guide you to your unique sense in design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn the rules. Not to follow them. To know what, when and how to break them. Be brave, make your own rules. Explore and see what you can do with design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grow tough skin! This world will be brutal at times. People will rip your design apart, change it, reject it. Don&apos;t let this process discourage you. Take these moments as opportunities for your growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earn! Don&apos;t shy away from earning with design. It is not an insult to your craft. Design gives so much to people and businesses, do not undervalue your contribution. Cherish the endless possibilities Design has to offer, earn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years will pass… If you do these and more, you&apos;ll find yourself in high places. The imposter syndrome will kick in, you will question your abilities. Don&apos;t give away to that inner voice! Look back at the years you put in the hard work with passion and the relationships you&apos;ve built. Acknowledge that your journey brought you there and you deserve it! Own it! Stay humble though and hungry, forever… There is always more to learn in design. This is a lifelong journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, Some days will be tough, some easy. You will need to do things you do not enjoy. Accept the design with everything it has to offer with ups and downs. When you stand back, take a moment and look at the big picture, you will see a beautiful life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never ever forget! There is more to design than the pixels you see on your screen. Develop your confidence, communication, negotiation, your human skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve every faith in you! You will have an amazing, rich, satisfying life with Design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Love&lt;br /&gt;
Oykun&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dear Young Designer,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designers, charge more $$$ to help yourself and your clients.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/charge-more.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designers, charge more $$$ to help yourself and your clients." /><published>2024-04-27T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-27T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/charge-more</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/charge-more.html">&lt;p&gt;Many designers shy away from increasing their rates, fearing it will scare clients away and put them under pressure to deliver higher-quality work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understandable concerns with the common fixed mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you want to grow as a Designer, you must be comfortable with losing the wrong type of clients who demand cheap and low-quality designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to level up and attract the right kind of clients. Type of clients who&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;value design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;value quality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are easy to work with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pay premium $$$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By charging higher rates, you are signalling to potential clients that you offer a level of expertise, professionalism and dedication that sets you apart from the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important detail though; I&apos;m not suggesting you charge more if your design doesn&apos;t deliver it. You need to master your skills first. After all, higher-value clients who pay premium $$$ will often come with a certain level of risk and expect higher quality work to lower that business risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&apos;t let this stress you though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since you are charging higher $$$ now, you can dedicate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more care&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will see how this approach influences the outcome of your work positively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By charging more, you are enabling yourself to deliver higher-quality work, as a positive consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By charging more, you are not helping only yourself with higher income, but your client with a higher quality of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By charging more, you are attracting the right type of clients who value design and trust your advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By charging more, you are becoming a better designer due to the environment it gives you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By charging more ...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a win-win situation for you and your clients!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charge More $$$!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Many designers shy away from increasing their rates, fearing it will scare clients away and put them under pressure to deliver higher-quality work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlock higher $$$ income with this approach as a Designer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/unlock-higher-income-with-this-approach-as-a-designer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlock higher $$$ income with this approach as a Designer" /><published>2024-02-25T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-25T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/unlock-higher-income-with-this-approach-as-a-designer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/unlock-higher-income-with-this-approach-as-a-designer.html">&lt;p&gt;You are a designer and want higher-value clients who pay higher $$$ dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m with you. We all do (in a way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you keep the $$$ income as the primary goal in your conversations with clients, it will completely affect your attitude, vibe...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are going to unintentionally keep bringing the subject to YOU and $. Not necessarily by directly saying that, but your questions and impatience will be around $. The client will sense that and may only be willing to pay a low to average $ amount, especially if you&apos;ve been preaching about your pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a mindset shift I need to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not sell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk to them just like you&apos;d do with a close friend of yours who wants to start a business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give them your genuine advice, thoughts, and tips about the business instead of talking only about your designs and portfolio and how much it will cost and what a great design you do and ...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brainstorm ideas about how you all can make a better product, what you can offer to clients, how you can position the offer in the market to go beyond the competition, how you can lower the cost to increase the revenue,...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Show them how you are focused on making their business a success, not your wallet thicker (yet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Share without the fear of revealing secrets. There are no secrets. Help them succeed with or without you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truly care for them and their business. They will see, sense that care. They will trust you for it. Then, money won&apos;t be an issue! They will pay you the best $$$ they can. They will recommend you to their friends and other businesses. They will be your best allies in the business world for other high-value projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Btw, I&apos;m not asking you to fake the care for a higher pay. You have to deliver for that trust! That&apos;s why this is a mindset shift instead of a 1-off tactic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For over 25 years in design, I&apos;ve approached people with this mindset, experiencing great satisfaction, making friends with various business owners, and earning $$$ millions of dollars along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, it&apos;s so difficult to find designers who take time with clients (better term: friends) and truly care for their team and business which makes it easier for you to stand out by doing it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You are a designer and want higher-value clients who pay higher $$$ dollars.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Practising distraction-free creativity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/practising-distraction-free-creativity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Practising distraction-free creativity" /><published>2024-02-21T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-21T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/practising-distraction-free-creativity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/practising-distraction-free-creativity.html">&lt;p&gt;The design world is filled with exciting opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see Designers on X who are creating Framer templates, experimenting with 3D, writing newsletters, starting design subscription agencies, selling icon packs and many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it&apos;s tempting to chase them all. I&apos;ve given in to that temptation as well, many times!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the saying goes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;We can do anything, but not everything&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written about &lt;a href=&quot;/tackling-fomo-driven-social-media-struggles&quot;&gt;Tackling FOMO-driven social media struggles&lt;/a&gt; for how to be okay with not chasing everything we see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s say you are set with 1 thing you want to do, however, now distractions usually come into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know how it is; You are decisive in creating a Framer template, you open Framer, then you get a notification from X, you tab on it, after 30mins you realize you have been browsing the feed. You go back to Framer, and while doing that, you see your Mail app, you have been waiting for an email, so you check, you find yourself spending another 30 minutes going through emails, and so on and on...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few practical tips that have kept me away from this endless cycle and helped me stay focused on my task;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/phone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;phone&quot; class=&quot;max-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Removing distractions from my phone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I turned off all the notifications on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no counts on the app icons, no Lock Screen notifications, nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complete silence. The only exception is the calls and messages from my wife and parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are no temptations to check what those numbers may hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/notes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;notes&quot; class=&quot;max-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Removing distractions from my laptop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep my MacBook as minimal as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to have multiple apps open. Randomly look at the mail app, click a link that opens Safari, more links in there, then an email notification, read that, then realise I spent 2 hours clicking around while I needed to write my book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m no longer running multiple apps at the same time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I&apos;m writing, I only have the Note app open.&lt;br /&gt;
If I&apos;m designing, I only have the Figma app open.&lt;br /&gt;
If I&apos;m replying to emails, I only have the Mail app open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also don&apos;t have anything on my desktop, in my downloads folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary goal nowadays is Writing the book. So all I have on my dock is the Notes app. When I open my laptop in the morning, that&apos;s the only option I see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/x.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;x&quot; class=&quot;max-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Removing distractions from Social media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may have noticed I only have X on my phone and notification is off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have started using it more as a one-way stream to share what I have to share and interact with the replies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also use Lists more intentionally now. I have lists for &quot;Readers of my books&quot;, &quot;Writing...&quot;, &quot;Designer Mindset Members&quot;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I don&apos;t get lost in endless consumption but create purposeful interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a day, I go through the &quot;For You&quot; tab as it gives me good suggestions and helps me explore new people to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you are primarily working on learning 3D design, you can create a list of 3D designers. This way, you won&apos;t be distracted by all other ideas that can be tempting. You can keep your focus and inspiration in one area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dash.png&quot; alt=&quot;dash&quot; class=&quot;max-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Removing distractions from Safari and Internet browsing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t have multiple tabs open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I&apos;m online to publish an article or send a newsletter like this one, I go to my Ghost dashboard and publish it. Then onto the next thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few of the many ways to help me stay focused on my creative endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As little context switching and distractions as possible. Setting up our environment for that plays a huge role in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Btw, it doesn&apos;t mean I don&apos;t have spontaneous fun with my digital products. I do, but it is a choice. I can have 20 tabs open while exploring on a Saturday night. However, not while I&apos;m trying to get work done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article could go on and on! But I will stop here for now as I want to keep it condensed to share the idea. If you find such tips useful, please do let me know by replying to this email. I&apos;m happy to expand on this further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Love&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The design world is filled with exciting opportunities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Letter with 10 Lessons</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023-letter-with-10-lessons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Letter with 10 Lessons" /><published>2023-12-30T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-30T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023-letter-with-10-lessons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023-letter-with-10-lessons.html">&lt;h3&gt;Write&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve been writing for years, however, I gave the focus it deserved in 2023 as I felt the urge to express my ideas more in words than colours and shapes. I didn&apos;t resist the urge and I have seen amazing benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Articulating my ideas, feelings, experiences, fears, aspirations, creativity, my &quot;self&quot; with words has made me an even more content, confident person and designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I failed to share them properly. Yes, I released the LettersFromADesigner eBook and have been getting amazing feedback, thank you! however, I failed to keep up with this Newsletter as I shifted my focus to writing on X. Not because I didn&apos;t have time or energy, but because I didn&apos;t want to be redundant here. That will change in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Reading fewer books deeply is more impactful than rushing through many instead&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is this unhinged badge of honour in readers&apos; world for reading the highest number of books in a year. They do speed reading or skim the book to finish it as quickly as possible and move on to the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was never one of those people, and I found myself reflecting on this idea more in 2023. This year I took the time to reread the books that have had the most impact on me. I read them slowly and took a moment off the book when I came across an inspiring section. I found a greater impact in this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Don&apos;t chase the numbers on social media, seek meaningful connections&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the year I took X somewhat seriously, especially in the second half of the year. I went against the common advice to grow rapidly and wrote what I truly cared about, despite often being perceived as abstract. It was mostly about the Designer Mindset. I didn&apos;t grow to the tens of thousands of followers. I didn&apos;t care for that, but I built meaningful connections with a few people that I will make the effort to stay in touch with for life. I&apos;m grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Don&apos;t let social media change you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We always talk about being authentic, however it is mostly empty talk. The desire to have a bigger number in our follower section beats the idea of authenticity. As a result, most do what gets likes even though that content may go against their worldview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;If you are not being truly yourself, what it meant for you won&apos;t be able to find you&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Go out more with people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an introvert, I find crowds and social activities pretty draining. However this year I made extra effort to join as many social events and meet as many people as I could. I made amazing connections, built relationships on a personal level, and had fun conversations, activities with people. It has been greatly rewarding for my well-being and confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Articulate your thoughts the way you want&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was writing the LettersFromADesigner eBook, I was hesitant about whether it would offend people, or if the language I used would make the message I was trying to convey unattractive. However, I didn&apos;t want to change the way I would say just to satisfy the way how traditional books do. I said it with a bit of tough love, as I say to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People found it refreshing, honest, and direct. I&apos;m relieved and grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Time spent with family is never a wasted time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I failed quite a few projects this year;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Consistency in this newsletter&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Updating uijar.com&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Finishing the first draft of Designer Mindset Book&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Publishing the podcasts I recorded&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Releasing FinalVer UI Kit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the list goes on...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I could hassle through at weekends to complete most of those. Perhaps you could put forward a good and convincing argument that I should have done so. I wouldn&apos;t have any strong logical response to that when you look from the business perspective as most do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I chose to spend the weekends with my family. Going to museums, walking in parks, taking my kids to a cafe with books, painting, playing video games, even just sitting around…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I feel the urge to get back at my side projects at a weekend, I remind myself how fast my kids are growing! Years pass like days. We have only about 16-17 years with them throughout their hopefully ~80 years of journey. Then they go to university, move out to their own home, and so on… I will have so many years that I will miss them! So while I have them here, I want to make the most of it. I can always write my book later, update side projects regularly, publish podcasts later, what I won&apos;t have later is the time with my kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&apos;m feeling deeply happy with my choice of keeping family above everything else while I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Focus on fewer than many&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, I was aspiring to do a lot in 2023 and I could do by putting in more working hours, but I chose not to do so as I kept family first. I often found myself questioning if I should spread myself thin and do many things in parallel, which I&apos;m used to, or focus on fewer things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have started giving a try to the latter approach and decided to focus on Writing Books for Designers. This enabled me to go deeper in the subject matter and I found this approach greatly satisfying. So, no more juggling between 10 things, but deep diving into max 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Helping others to design can be more satisfying than designing myself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have mentored and coached designers at any level from aspiring designers to Senior and Director levels for many years. They have seen great results from these relations and excelled in their career. However these interactions were at the conversational level, the other party had to create opportunities and take action. I always wanted to go beyond conversations to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I hesitantly took the &quot;Manager&quot; role for a few designers. I was hesitant because I was warned that it would take significant time and focus from my craft. Very quickly, I found the vast satisfaction of creating opportunities and environments for designers to grow and have more fun with design. I was able to go beyond words and actually shape teams, projects in an ideal way for these designers to practise and grow certain skills, mostly human skills such as confidence, communication, resilience, and they did. I fell in love with this side of design and I&apos;m looking forward to having more impact on more designers&apos; journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;More Silence than Noise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to consume out there, from podcasts to YouTube videos, movies, social media posts and more. It is very easy to fall into the trap of hopelessly trying to catch up with all of them and to do so, we don&apos;t let our EarPods leave our ears and constantly fill our brain with media. The common idea is to &quot;add more to be more&quot;. However, what it does is just creating noise and shallowness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve eliminated a lot of noise in 2023. I removed my EarPods and directed my eyes to the real world over constant lights from YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave my &quot;self&quot; time and space to process and reflect on what I read and experienced. I went deeper than wider. I learned a lot about myself with this approach. I learned a lot more from the fewer things than I would from overwhelming many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m definitely going to be practising this more, increasingly…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot more to go over, but I&apos;m going to stop here for now. I&apos;m happy to share more if you like to read such personal insights. Please let me know by replying to this email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Be unapologetically yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Write! Your dreams, fears, experiences, reflections, worldview…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Prioritise family over everything else.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Grow in meaningful connections over numbers.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Give your mind and heart the time and space to process what you&apos;ve already engaged with.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Help others, you may find love in there.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Engage with fewer meaningful over consuming many shallow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Write I&apos;ve been writing for years, however, I gave the focus it deserved in 2023 as I felt the urge to express my ideas more in words than colours and shapes. I didn&apos;t resist the urge and I have seen amazing benefits.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tackling FOMO-driven social media struggle with your new Designer Mindset</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tackling-fomo-driven-social-media-struggle-with-your-new-designer-mindset.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tackling FOMO-driven social media struggle with your new Designer Mindset" /><published>2023-09-30T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-30T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tackling-fomo-driven-social-media-struggle-with-your-new-designer-mindset</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tackling-fomo-driven-social-media-struggle-with-your-new-designer-mindset.html">&lt;p&gt;You are a designer, working on your full-time job or your freelance projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You go online, open X app. You see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;John released his Framer template&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Fatma launches her &quot;How To Make $100k As A Designer&quot; course&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Gary starts his subscription model design service&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Laila is working on an AI product&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Nadia posts screenshots from her Stripe with $50k monthly sale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, you look at yourself and feel like you are missing out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think you should be working on your framer template, course, UIKit, … all of it! Otherwise, you are falling behind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From your perspective, you look at X as 1 thing, almost like a single person is doing it all. Then you look at yourself, doing only 1 thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FOMO crips in. You start to feel less of yourself and get demotivated, even depressed perhaps!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds familiar? You are not alone! We all struggle with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today&apos;s hyper-connected world, where social media paints our eyes and minds with a constant stream of achievements, updates, and seemingly perfect lives, it&apos;s easy to fall into FOMO-induced depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear of missing out on opportunities, experiences, and success can lead to comparison, anxiety, self-doubt and more...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a few ways of approaching this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;FIRST&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change your perspective!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at it at the individual level. 1 person usually does 1 thing first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 thing well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it&apos;s successful, then it is easier to create a course on teaching that thing, or take out the components from it, and repackage them as a kit to sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the side outcomes of the 1 thing that doesn&apos;t really take that much effort. You have already covered most of it with your 1 thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look again at that designer on X with this eye. You will see this pattern more often than not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find your 1 thing and focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&apos;t worry about the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will come naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;SECOND&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embrace the mindset of JOMO (Joy Of Missing Out) over FOMO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of feeling bad about what you&apos;re not doing, focus on the thing you are doing well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JOMO says, &quot;Hey, let&apos;s be happy about what we&apos;re doing right now!&quot; yes, a bit cringe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&apos;t have to copy what everyone else is doing. You can focus on your own ideas and make them shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mindset also helps us to use social media in a better way. We don&apos;t have to spend forever looking at other people&apos;s various stuff. We can choose the ones that are relevant to the 1 thing we are making and keep the focus on it without distractions. It is okay to unfollow and block people who are not truly relevant to you at where you are in your journey today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it sounds like supernatural nonsense; saying &quot;Just change the way to look at it!&quot; However, the power of mindset is often overlooked. I encourage you to be open-minded, please.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;THIRD&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoic philosopher and emperor Epictetus says;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It&apos;s not what happens to you, but how you react to it that matters.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This profound mindset emphasises that while we may not always have control over the events that occur in our lives, we always have the power to choose our responses to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and people like this is going to be around us, we will be constantly exposed to these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have no control over what other people are doing, sharing, saying... What we have control over is our reaction to it. That goes through setting our Designer Mindset straight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just a few ways to approach it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Changing your perspective from a collective effort to a single effort&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Embracing the JOMO by enjoying what you&apos;re doing without worrying about what everyone else is doing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Taking the Stoic approach to taking control of how we react to the events happening in our lives that are out of our control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You are a designer, working on your full-time job or your freelance projects.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hustle Culture for Designers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/hustle-culture-for-designers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hustle Culture for Designers" /><published>2023-09-23T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-23T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/hustle-culture-for-designers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/hustle-culture-for-designers.html">&lt;p&gt;We all have our aspirations and goals in life and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it goes from having an impact on my full-time work to helping designers via my blog, email newsletter, and other educational content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to work damn hard to achieve these goals! Making the most of every breathing hour! Time is working against me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, yes and no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, considering the very little chance you haven&apos;t heard of the Hustle Culture;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Hustle culture is a term that refers to the belief that working long hours and pushing yourself to the limit is the key to success.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is about working hard. That&apos;s a good thing, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with everything in life, it depends on who you are, and where you are in your life and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did my share of hustling (I don&apos;t like this term btw) and it worked out well for a period of time but only because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I was young&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I had the energy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I didn&apos;t have any dependents&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I didn&apos;t have many commitments&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I had time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as I&apos;m 40 years old with a family, a full-time job and loads of responsibilities on my plate, I find it hard to hustle long nights for a long period of time. I don&apos;t even want to any more even though the current culture tries to make you feel guilty for not hustling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Working Smart&quot; became my solution to my younger&apos;s self&apos;s &quot;Working Hard&quot; approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, you need to be Smart to work smart, and you need to Work Hard to be smart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is not really a choice of one or another, but more of a progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you work hard, you learn what works and what doesn&apos;t, you gain experience, and then you transition to working smart, intentionally or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do you go about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a 20 years old aspiring designer spending hours every day on TikTok or PlayStation, it can be good to hustle a bit and learn. Make the most of your time and energy for your growth while you have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Btw, I&apos;m a firm believer in moderation. Video games, social media, Netflix are not evil! unless you spend countless hours for them every day. I enjoy my PlayStation time pretty much every day but in moderation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a 40 years old designer with kids and a full-time job, hustling long nights for a long period of time can drive you to burnout. It can affect your family life. It may be smarter to develop a better plan for growth than brut hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember; Hustle Culture is not sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to characterise this as more of an Obsession than Hustle. I often obsess over things. When I do, I buy all the recommended books, I research, watch videos, practice it, and obsess over it! It usually lasts a couple of weeks or a few months. Then to the next thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this approach healthier because my drive is purely based on my interest, not any external force. It is an &quot;I want to...&quot; situation, not &quot;I should do...&quot;. So burnout is less likely to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the obsession slowly goes away, I take my learnings, seal them in my skill set and move on to the next thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you do, please take your rest as seriously as your hustle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a creative field like ours, we can actually get more done by taking more breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&apos;t worry about putting names on things like Hustle Culture and comparing yourself to how others define it, including me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to your body. Hear your ambitions. If you feel the fire for obsessing over anything, go for it. Spend extra hours for a while to learn while the motivation is high! It won&apos;t last long. Don&apos;t compare yourself to others, and feel depressed. Everybody&apos;s circumstances are different. You do You. Work hard and Work smart in your own way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We all have our aspirations and goals in life and career.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Visual Design Matters</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/why-visual-design-matters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Visual Design Matters" /><published>2023-06-24T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-24T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/why-visual-design-matters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/why-visual-design-matters.html">&lt;p&gt;Visual Design often doesn&apos;t receive the respect it deserves among other disciplines such as UX, Development, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have faced situations like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Devs have already started the development based on UX. Just spend a few hours adding colours, please.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We do not need visual design. Our devs are building based on the UX and it works.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We do not have a budget for a visual designer. We have more important things to spend our money on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the list goes on...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sad thing is that this lack of appreciation doesn&apos;t only come from the product itself, which naturally may not understand the value of visual design, but also from the visual designers themselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve had unfortunate conversations where visual designers expressed their desire to switch to UX because they believed there was no value in Visual Design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you expect people to respect your profession if you don&apos;t respect it yourself in the first place? So, I often find myself explaining the value of Visual Design to product owners, businesses, and other designers. Once I explain it, they understand why it matters and begin to appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few arguments I put forward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;①  Beauty Matters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Businesses often approach products with logic, and that is okay. However, we don&apos;t always require a logical or mathematical explanation for everything in business. As humans, we have always appreciated beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself: Do you prefer a beautiful chair or an ugly one? Both chairs will function as intended, but you will naturally be drawn to one. Why is that?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This preference for beauty extends beyond chairs and applies to various aspects of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In business, visual design has the power to create a memorable and immersive experience for customers. It goes beyond mere functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When businesses prioritise visual design alongside logic and functionality, they can resonate with individuals on a deeper level. By embracing the value of visual design, businesses can elevate their offerings and leave a lasting impression on their target audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Left: Classic Eames Lounge Chair &amp;amp; Ottoman - Right: unknown&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;②  Positive Emotion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beauty creates positive emotions. People with positive emotions are more forgiving of flaws and more creative in solving problems they face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do you think we have zero patience when an ugly government website dysfunctions, but we are more forgiving when a beautifully designed product messes up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of beauty on our emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty has a way of uplifting our spirits and creating positive feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we come across an ugly and dysfunctional government website, it fails to evoke any positive emotional response. As a result, our patience wears thin, and we quickly become frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, when a beautifully designed product encounters a hiccup, our positive emotions from its attractive design still linger. This helps soften the blow and makes us more understanding of the temporary glitch. We tend to attribute it to the complexities of technology rather than seeing it as a major flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This just goes to show how the power of beauty can influence our level of patience and forgiveness in different situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Left: Unknown - Right: Stripe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;③  Leading Competition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most likely, your product is not the only one in the market solving the same problem for people. So, how are you supposed to beat the competition? Features and prices are the first aspects that come to mind...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, beauty is the key. People make purchasing decisions based on emotions, not just logic. If you design the most beautiful product in the market, you can lead the competition, even if you lack certain features or have a higher price. Just take a look at Apple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a product captures our attention with its stunning design, it creates a desire within us. Beauty has the power to spark that emotional connection and make us fall in love with a product. It&apos;s this emotional bond that drives us to choose it over others, regardless of its technical specifications or price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you want to stand out and lead the competition, remember that beauty has a magnetic effect on people&apos;s hearts and minds. Embrace the power of design, and watch your product lead the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Left: iOS - Right: Android&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;④  Increased Revenue&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best arguments you can put forward for business owners! : )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They always want to spend less and profit more. It is a business after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the points mentioned above and more, focusing on design and other factors that set your offering apart can attract a larger customer base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means more people choose your product over competitors in the market, resulting in increased revenue. It&apos;s a win-win situation where prioritising design and delivering an exceptional user experience can directly impact your bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, invest in creating a standout product that not only meets customer needs but also delights them, and watch your revenue grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;APPLE vs SAMSUNG - Source data: FourWeekMBA Financials&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;⑤  Attracting Talent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you build successful products? &quot;With talented people&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you attract talented people? Offering more money is not always possible or enough. Remember, it&apos;s not only about money; it&apos;s about being part of a team that creates beautiful, remarkable products and achieves remarkable success.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Visual Design often doesn&apos;t receive the respect it deserves among other disciplines such as UX, Development, and so on.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1 Simple Approach to Discover Your Design Career Path</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/1-simple-approach-to-discover-your-design-career-path.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1 Simple Approach to Discover Your Design Career Path" /><published>2023-05-30T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-30T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/1-simple-approach-to-discover-your-design-career-path</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/1-simple-approach-to-discover-your-design-career-path.html">&lt;p&gt;As designers, we can sometimes feel lost in our design career and it applies to all of us from Junior to Senior levels. We either have no idea where we are going or get lazy and lost in our comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I&apos;ve based the advice purely on my self-experience, it&apos;d go like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems over Goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set up systems, constantly push yourself out of your comfort zone, and it&apos;ll lead you on a clear path to success. You don&apos;t need specific goals since goals are often changing, either due to the environment we live in or the skills we gain along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This&apos;s been my path. I didn&apos;t have specific short-term goals, I just wanted to be the best designer I can be. I pushed myself to do better with every project and it&apos;s always led me to a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, whenever I give this advice, I see most people looking at me with confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are looking for a more specific, step-by-step guide. Something more actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t want to selfishly advise you only what worked for me. After all, everybody is different. I have seen different approaches that worked for many other designers I interacted with. One of the most common ones that I have seen success in among others goes as below;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Setting a specific, clear goal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know! It goes against what I wrote above, however as I said, everybody is different and I&apos;m open to suggesting different solutions as long as I see enough people see success with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK. Then comes the question; &quot;but Oykun, I don&apos;t know what goal to set!&quot; There are many reasons for this situation and mindset from a lack of experimentation and reading to networking, observing and more…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to discover your goal such as exploring your interests, strengths, and values, as well as gaining experience in different areas of design and experimenting with various design projects to determine what resonates with you the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These would be the better ways to discover goals for some, however, these require self-discovery as a designer and it takes time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s keep it simple for now: Don&apos;t overcomplicate by trying to find the one and only grand goal and purpose in life. It is too much to take on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you need to do is to look at designers you aspire to and reverse engineer their journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will give you a 2 step formula!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Step 1: Make a list of designers you aspire to and choose one.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need you to be careful with who you are aspiring though. Don&apos;t be fooled by the glamorous life they present on social media. Look at their background to see where their experience is coming from, read their writings to see what they are sharing, study them...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Step 2: Research their journey to reverse engineer.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do they work at a company you are sympathetic to as Senior Product Designers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that&apos;s where you see yourself, set your goal for that specific company and role, then start researching what it takes to get a job there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s say this person is a Senior Designer at Apple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I. Find them on Linkedin, and look at their career journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where did they work? Agency background? Find that agency&apos;s website and projects they did.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Find more designers in the same role on Linkedin, and study their journey as well.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Find the similarities.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Place yourself in this roadmap, but do it honestly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;II. Find their work on Dribbble, Behance, and more...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Study their portfolio.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Look at their designs before and after joining that company.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You will start seeing areas you will need to improve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;III. Follow them on social media, subscribe to their newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Start interacting with them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Learn from them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Teach them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Discover the way they think and approach design, not only what they do, but WHY they do.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Read the books they recommend to get a better understanding of the mindset they have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IV. Research the interview process for that specific role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;There are countless articles, and YouTube videos you can find that share tips for specific roles.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Consume them, practise them, learn them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. Don&apos;t be afraid to reach these people to ask direct advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;But, don&apos;t just ask a vague question like &quot;I want a job there, can you help me?&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It is too broad!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ask direct and simple questions such as &quot;What is 1 thing I should include in my case studies to get an interview at Apple?&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You will be surprised how kind people are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VI. You see! You are already following a specific direction. You don&apos;t seem lost now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK here is the catch; As you accumulate all this knowledge, you have to be disciplined and work hard!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t mean missing dinner with your family and working long hours, no! Fewer but quality hours with focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on your weaknesses. Is it technical skills? Find resources to study and practise. Is it soft skills, same...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the path you are going for, you can also have a look at the Twitter Thread I wrote about interviewing tips&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, let&apos;s test this approach with a different example;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s say, you don&apos;t like that corporate path and aspire to be a solopreneur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same steps;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I. Find solopreneurs who build similar products to your ideal ones.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;II. Find out the skills they possess.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;III. Spot your weaknesses and study them. Marketing, Coding, Copywriting...&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;IV. Reach out to them if you need to&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;V. Keep building your product as you learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything is learnable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reverse engineer the good examples!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I would argue that the self-discovery approach would be a more reliable way for some. After all, everybody is different. However, that route takes time, effort, and inner strength... It is a more philosophical approach. I can deep dive into that in another article if you are interested. Not to worry though, you will be getting better at that as you follow the simpler path we deep-dived into here : )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK! This is the simple way to start exploring your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you see, you can not just sit and expect your goal, your purpose in life to come to you from the blue sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to look for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you find it, you have to work hard for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As designers, we can sometimes feel lost in our design career and it applies to all of us from Junior to Senior levels. We either have no idea where we are going or get lazy and lost in our comfort zone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Communicate Value over Long Hours of Work as a Designer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/communicate-value-over-long-hours-of-work-as-a-designer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Communicate Value over Long Hours of Work as a Designer" /><published>2023-05-23T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-23T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/communicate-value-over-long-hours-of-work-as-a-designer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/communicate-value-over-long-hours-of-work-as-a-designer.html">&lt;p&gt;The tagline for my newsletter goes as below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Grow As Designer | Helping Designers Grow Their Value and Income.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s a bit unclear, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the heck is &quot;Value&quot; anyway? How can you grow it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there are many meanings to it and ways to grow it for a designer, but let&apos;s focus on how you can grow your value by communicating the work you do in the right way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let me make something very clear:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;You don&apos;t get paid for your work or time.&lt;br /&gt;
You get paid for the value you bring.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read that again, please. A few times actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you apply for a job, you might be thinking, &quot;I&apos;ll work 8 hours a day, 5 days a week, do some design work that&apos;s assigned to me, and get paid $40k a year.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business owner thinks differently, &quot;Oykun is applying for a job. Can he solve our complex design problems? Design is crucial for this project, can he provide top-quality work?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spot the difference in these two sentences. Yes, the whole f*** thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&apos;re focused on the input (time and work), but the business owner is focused on the outcome (value).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you wonder why you didn&apos;t get the job or are not getting paid well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can talk for hours about how hard you work, how many hours you put into your work... These mean nothing to very little to the business owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start talking about how you can improve their business with design, and they will be all ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need you to change the way you look at design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need you to look at the design from the value perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give you a clear example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an agency world, you can often see junior or senior designers working damn hard for long hours, doing an amazing job and getting paid less than the creative director who does the usual working hours. Or you can work as a waitress 12 hours a day. It is noble and hard work, but you won&apos;t earn as much as an experienced designer earns in 1 hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t mean to put the money as the core criterion here. There is more to what we do and why we do it than the money. However, this simplifies things to make a point here, plus let&apos;s be honest, for some money is the main reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as a result;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Working hard or long doesn&apos;t determine how much you earn.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you may say; &quot;OK, Oykun, but how can I use this for my benefit today as a designer?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few aspects from doing the &quot;valuable design work&quot; to communicating the &quot;value in your design&quot; and more...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s focus on the latter now by changing the way you communicate your design work to your existing or new potential clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s look at both cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Case 1: You&apos;re a full-time designer talking to your employer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be saying: &quot;I stayed till late past few days in the office to finish this. It was a lot of work, it took me 3 days. I think it does the job well.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your employer might think: &quot;OK. Get to the point. What did you design?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, saying something like this would benefit you vastly better:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You: &quot;I put in extra hours yesterday to design this new direction where we enable users to achieve their goals with less friction. This can differentiate our offer from the competition.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employer: &quot;That&apos;s cool! Let&apos;s explore that. What other ideas do you have? What do you need to explore these ideas?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Case 2: You&apos;re a freelance designer talking to a potential client&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;I&apos;m the hardest working designer you will ever find. I will put in all the hours and hard work for this project.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Client in his head: &quot;Yes, yes, OK. You work hard. Are you going to ask me to pay for the more hours? Why more hours? What about the outcome? ...&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You focused on the input, time and hard work, which doesn&apos;t mean much to the client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You: &quot;I understand you are trying to achieve goal x with this SaaS product for the y type of user. There are various ways I&apos;d approach delivering a solution via design. However, based on my limited knowledge for the time being, direction z may be a good place to start with. This would enable users to complete their task with less friction.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Client: &quot;OK! Interesting idea! That could work well, especially for the user type c. I wonder what other ideas she has!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential client is all ears now! You are communicating the value you can bring, not what a hard-working designer you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mind-blowing part is that; the work you do can be the exact same design in both cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes all it takes to earn 5x times more is how you phrase it, and how you communicate your design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses are interested in the outcome and value while most designers focus on communicating the input by time and work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communicate the value and the outcome of your design!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I promise it will lead you to increased income, opportunities, respect, satisfaction, influence and more...&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The tagline for my newsletter goes as below: Grow As Designer | Helping Designers Grow Their Value and Income.</summary></entry></feed>