<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-16T07:40:33+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Oykun Yilmaz</title><subtitle>Designer based in London.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How I read more books</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/how-i-read-more-books.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I read more books" /><published>2021-05-15T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-15T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/how-i-read-more-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/how-i-read-more-books.html">&lt;h2&gt;Replacing smartphone with a book.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all want to read more and we always struggle finding time for it. I used to be in the same situation and feel guilty of not reading enough. After all, how could I even find time with 2 kids, day time job, multiple side projects, list goes on... &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then this happened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;During the past few months, I replaced my phone with a book and this happened 📚+ kindle.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Whenever I had a moment here and there, while waiting in line, walking to tube, lunch time, ... I grabbed my book instead of phone. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It turns out I actually have had enough time to read 🤷‍♂️ &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/eURbLh47Sb&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/eURbLh47Sb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; oykun.com (@oykun) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oykun/status/1196430204081725441?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;November 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it is an old tweet and it proves the effectiveness as it still stands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think that we need to spare a big chunk of time during the day to read. Yes, that would be ideal but if you can&apos;t do that, use the little bits of 5-10 minutes here and there in your day to read. It quickly adds up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, we no longer have as much opportunity since the Covid lockdowns have started. I no longer commute to work, however I still have that time in my day, it is up to me to choose how to use it. Plus I still have lots of opportunities here and there, on the way to school to pick up kids, while walking to shops, waiting in line for grocery, waiting sleep to kick in after getting in bed, list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few simple tips that have helped me to read more;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Always carry a book. Kindle or physical.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Pick up your book instead of your phone when you have a moment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Once you start using these bits of time to read, you will naturally want to create time for reading as you fall back in love with reading and want to finish that page, section, then the whole book. &lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Replacing smartphone with a book.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-howireadmore.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-howireadmore.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Get up when you Wake up</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/get-up-when-you-wake-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Get up when you Wake up" /><published>2021-04-30T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-30T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/get-up-when-you-wake-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/get-up-when-you-wake-up.html">&lt;h2&gt;We all have 24 hours in a day. Entrepreneur to 5 products and 4 kids with well balanced life or a single full time employee who struggles to find time to do a simple reading/writing.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my previous post about &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/new-challanges.html&quot; title=&quot;New Challenges&quot;&gt;New Challenges&lt;/a&gt;, I have started a full time job after many years of freelancing. One of the first challenges I&apos;ve been facing is better time and energy management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I used to freelance, I was was able to work on multiple things during the day including my personal projects, client projects, accounting errands, home errands, so on... However my current role in the Investment Banking requires me to join many meetings during the day and make sure that product teams have the designs they need to proceed in agreed timelines. So, once the working hours start, I&apos;m 100% in this full time work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggled to manage personal projects and errands during the first few weeks. I can no longer do long nights to catch up on things. At least for now, it is how it is. I ran out of energy and creativity after a long day of work and meetings. I&apos;m hoping to adjust to this new pace in coming days and weeks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for now what I do is, &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;I get up when I wake up.&lt;/strong&gt; I know it sounds silly, however I believe it applies to most of us, alarm goes off or we just wake up but we waste 10, 15+ mins turning in bed if not longer, fall asleep for 5mins, wake up again, so on and on... You don&apos;t get the rest you are after nor use the time for something productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I just get up as soon as I wake up. I put my alarm for 5:30am, but I guess my mental alarm works better after a few days of training and I wake up sometime between 5:00 and 5:30am. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives me about 1.5 hours before kids wake up and all the meetings start. I must say I don&apos;t remember when I was so productive last time! There is something magical about that early morning with fresh mind. I get so much done in that ~1h and I&apos;m looking forward to expand it 2h+. I&apos;ll try getting up 5am next week, and move to 4:30am next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no much I want to do out of work without neglecting my family and personal health. I still get to spend time with my kids after work, and time with my wife after kids go to bed, and while everybody is in sleep in early morning, I have my time to do whatever I see value at; read, write, code, design, ...&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We all have 24 hours in a day. Entrepreneur to 5 products and 4 kids with well balanced life or a single full time employee who struggles to find time to do a simple reading/writing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-getup.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-getup.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Challenges</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/new-challanges.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Challenges" /><published>2021-04-26T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-26T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/new-challanges</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/new-challanges.html">&lt;h2&gt;Don&apos;t fear to take new challenges bigger than you&apos;ve ever dealt with. Remember, we don&apos;t grow when things are easy, we grow when we face challenges.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more of a personal update article. I wanted to document my thought process behind this radical decision I have taken in my career. A direction I thought I&apos;d never take. I guess &quot;Never Say Never&quot; proves itself true again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have accepted a job offer from a Tier 1 Investment Bank as a Vice President of Design role to work on Design Systems and Financial Product designs that heavily relies on data. This has been my first month and yes I certainly have taken a challenge! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m a self taught designer and (used-to-be) developer. The way I&apos;ve learned all my skills has been by taking new challenges in the real world with real projects. I&apos;ve written more about that earlier at &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oykun.com/2013/self-taught-with-passion.html&quot; title=&quot;Self-taught with Passion&quot;&gt;Self-taught with Passion&lt;/a&gt;&quot;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, but why? Well, things have been going a bit too well in my freelance world. I have had lots of interesting projects coming through, I have met new people, made good earning, had my own schedule... All and all good, I&apos;m very grateful for all of it but the biggest challenge I was able to take was based on the projects, and all I was able to improve with those were technical skills. However I wanted to learn a completely new business and focus more on improving my soft skills in an another level such as time-management, presentation, communication, managing teams and projects in a new environment, working with people in person... This job offer has it all and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be sharing my learnings in the coming weeks and months in this blog. However so far, I love the difficult and challenging situation I&apos;ve put myself in! There is so much I need to learn and improve to make this job going as well as my freelancing experience. I&apos;m excited to improve myself and share with you all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Don&apos;t fear to take new challenges bigger than you&apos;ve ever dealt with. Remember, we don&apos;t grow when things are easy, we grow when we face challenges. This is more of a personal update article. I wanted to document my thought process behind this radical decision I have taken in my career. A direction I thought I&apos;d never take. I guess &quot;Never Say Never&quot; proves itself true again.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-challenge.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-challenge.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How do I get my best projects?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/how-do-i-get-my-best-projects.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do I get my best projects?" /><published>2021-02-21T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-21T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/how-do-i-get-my-best-projects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/how-do-i-get-my-best-projects.html">&lt;h2&gt;It is not What you know but Who!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should probably cover this subject in a series of articles. For today I wanted to write about the important of connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday while I was playing Final Fantasy 7 Remake, I heard Tifa saying Cloud about the importance of making connections to get more jobs and she was encouraging Cloud to meet more people in Midgar city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is so relatable to our creative industry, to any industry actually. You can be a highly experienced and skilled designer, but if you don&apos;t have connections, you may struggle to get the lead for that dream project of yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;You need to be the first name that comes to mind when someone needs a designer.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve that you need to put yourself out there. Share your work, experiments, experiences at the platforms like Instagram, Dribbble, Twitter, etc where you can make connections. You need to actively build connections and meet as many people as possible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Trust is the key! A potential client would be willing to pay more to a designer with less experience, but recommended by a trusted friend. A less risky option is more valuable to a client&apos;s business.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;mb5&quot;&gt;I have involved in hundreds of projects in my ~20 years of experience, and the bigger part of the best projects I have involved came from recommendations. It usually starts like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;indent-speech&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi Oykun, you have worked with one of my friend, he was impressed with the work you did for him and recommended me to contact you...&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;indent-speech&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi Oykun, I need a design work and the designer I always work with isn&apos;t available at the momet and she recommended I reach out to you as she has been following your work...&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;indent-speech&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi Oykun, I have been following your work for a while, and now that I&apos;m building my own business, I thought I would reach out to you...&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;mt5&quot;&gt;If you can put yourself in this position, you will already beat the 90% of competition. Now you just need to build your relation with the potential client in a friendly way and share how you can improve their product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investing time in improving technical skills is very important, but make sure to give enough time to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Make connections, Share your work and the dream projects will find you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is not What you know but Who! I should probably cover this subject in a series of articles. For today I wanted to write about the important of connections. Yesterday while I was playing Final Fantasy 7 Remake, I heard Tifa saying Cloud about the importance of making connections to get more jobs and she was encouraging Cloud to meet more people in Midgar city. It is so relatable to our creative industry, to any industry actually. You can be a highly experienced and skilled designer, but if you don&apos;t have connections, you may struggle to get the lead for that dream project of yours. You need to be the first name that comes to mind when someone needs a designer. To achieve that you need to put yourself out there. Share your work, experiments, experiences at the platforms like Instagram, Dribbble, Twitter, etc where you can make connections. You need to actively build connections and meet as many people as possible. Trust is the key! A potential client would be willing to pay more to a designer with less experience, but recommended by a trusted friend. A less risky option is more valuable to a client&apos;s business. I have involved in hundreds of projects in my ~20 years of experience, and the bigger part of the best projects I have involved came from recommendations. It usually starts like this: &quot;Hi Oykun, you have worked with one of my friend, he was impressed with the work you did for him and recommended me to contact you...&quot; &quot;Hi Oykun, I need a design work and the designer I always work with isn&apos;t available at the momet and she recommended I reach out to you as she has been following your work...&quot; &quot;Hi Oykun, I have been following your work for a while, and now that I&apos;m building my own business, I thought I would reach out to you...&quot; If you can put yourself in this position, you will already beat the 90% of competition. Now you just need to build your relation with the potential client in a friendly way and share how you can improve their product. Investing time in improving technical skills is very important, but make sure to give enough time to Make connections, Share your work and the dream projects will find you.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-network.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-network.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Heroes over Mentors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/heroes-over-mentors.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heroes over Mentors" /><published>2021-02-15T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/heroes-over-mentors</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/heroes-over-mentors.html">&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve never had a mentor, but I&apos;ve had heroes. I&apos;ve put myself in their shoes when I need to make design or business decisions. I&apos;ve worked hard to align quality of my work to my heroes. I can&apos;t mention a single name, there have been so many of them. Btw, it doesn&apos;t have to be for the design industry, isn&apos;t it same when we are trying to be a better parent or partner, taking examples from our own parents or so... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we have an amazing community who is more than happy to help each other. I personally know designers from big corporations to individual freelancers offering free mentoring. In my 20 years of experience, I have received countless emails, messages asking for advice. I&apos;m humbled by it and I have been doing my very best to respond every one of them in my limited time. This is one of the reason why I have started this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this ease of communication also made the contribution from some experienced designers more challenging. There is just not enough time to respond all, mentor all individually. We should not be discouraged with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;We do not need to be in active communication with our heros (which would make them mentors), however we can follow their work, blog, Twitter, etc. to have an understanding of what they are up to, how they are approaching to certain situations and learn from them.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can have countless heroes to learn from instead of waiting for a space in one&apos;s already tight calendar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Let&apos;s share what we learn and be a Hero to someone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I&apos;ve never had a mentor, but I&apos;ve had heroes. I&apos;ve put myself in their shoes when I need to make design or business decisions. I&apos;ve worked hard to align quality of my work to my heroes. I can&apos;t mention a single name, there have been so many of them. Btw, it doesn&apos;t have to be for the design industry, isn&apos;t it same when we are trying to be a better parent or partner, taking examples from our own parents or so... Today we have an amazing community who is more than happy to help each other. I personally know designers from big corporations to individual freelancers offering free mentoring. In my 20 years of experience, I have received countless emails, messages asking for advice. I&apos;m humbled by it and I have been doing my very best to respond every one of them in my limited time. This is one of the reason why I have started this blog. However, this ease of communication also made the contribution from some experienced designers more challenging. There is just not enough time to respond all, mentor all individually. We should not be discouraged with this. We do not need to be in active communication with our heros (which would make them mentors), however we can follow their work, blog, Twitter, etc. to have an understanding of what they are up to, how they are approaching to certain situations and learn from them. We can have countless heroes to learn from instead of waiting for a space in one&apos;s already tight calendar. Let&apos;s share what we learn and be a Hero to someone.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-heroes.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-heroes.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Look Good, Feel Good</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/look-good-feel-good.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Look Good, Feel Good" /><published>2021-02-08T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/look-good-feel-good</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/look-good-feel-good.html">&lt;h2&gt;An overlooked factor in keeping a good mood while working from home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us, designers, are working from home now and we are lucky to be able to do that. However it certainly comes with its challenges with staying creative and motivated. Especially if you are not used to work from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many factors to it from not having enough sleep to not having a separate work space, necessary tools, fast broadband connection, so on... These are all acceptable reasons, but there is one overlooked factor I believe, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Look good, feel good.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to fall in the trap of staying in PJs whole day long. This can sound amazing at first. I&apos;m sure you have heard freelancers bragging about &lt;i&gt;&quot;Working in my boxes 🙃&quot;&lt;/i&gt;. While this is technically possible, I find it very demotivating.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flex flex-wrap justify-between mt5 mb5&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;w-40-l&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CG5MsDkACkh/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lookgood-feelgood-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Instagram @oykun&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;w-40-l&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CHLN7M9gWlT/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lookgood-feelgood-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Instagram @oykun&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the bigger part of my career, I have been working from home and I built some habits in years to stay productive and creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Every morning I dress up like going to office. Not necessarily putting on smart suits, but clean and comfortable clothes that I feel good in. This helps me to feel good and do a better job in my design work.  &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may not an effective factor for every one out there, but I hope at least this can make to question some simple and overlooked factors of yours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s keep in good mood. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An overlooked factor in keeping a good mood while working from home</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-feelgood.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-feelgood.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coding this blog on iPad</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/coding-this-blog-on-ipad.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coding this blog on iPad" /><published>2021-02-01T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/coding-this-blog-on-ipad</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/coding-this-blog-on-ipad.html">&lt;div class=&quot;max-width&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I have been coding this simple Jekyll blog on my iPad as well as my MBP and I wanted to share my flow. This is not going to be a detailed post explaining every steps in details, but an overall flow. I can get in more details in a separate post maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I build this website in a very simple, lightweight way by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot; title=&quot;Jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; and hosting on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com&quot; title=&quot;Github Pages&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; for free.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;This system allows me to run this blog without managing any database. I enjoy the simplicity and security of this system. This also makes it easy to manage from my iPad, all I need is a Git client and my choice is &lt;a href=&quot;https://workingcopyapp.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Working Copy App&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;mt5 mb0&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;After I installed the app on my iPad, I entered my Github details and it listed all my repos. Then, all I needed to do was selecting the repo and Clone.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;img-grey-bg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coding-on-ipad-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working copy app on iPad&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;mt5 mb0&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Now I can edit my codes, create new files using the app. There are separate iOS IDEs that you can use, but I&apos;m fine with the WorkingCopy, plus I don&apos;t want to over-complicate the flow.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;img-grey-bg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coding-on-ipad-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working copy app on iPad&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;mt5 mb0&quot;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Once I&apos;m done with the code updates, I hit Commit, write my commit message and Push.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coding-on-ipad-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working copy app on iPad&quot; class=&quot;center mb3&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;p class=&quot;mt3&quot;&gt;That&apos;s all :) Github Pages takes care of the rest and the updates go live in less than a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;When I need to continue on my MBP, I first do Git Pull to get the updates. The same applies to my iPad, I do Pull after making a Push from my MBP. So, both system gets the latest code and there is no conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;BTW, the same flow works on my iPhone as well.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have been coding this simple Jekyll blog on my iPad as well as my MBP and I wanted to share my flow. This is not going to be a detailed post explaining every steps in details, but an overall flow. I can get in more details in a separate post maybe. I build this website in a very simple, lightweight way by using Jekyll and hosting on Github Pages for free. This system allows me to run this blog without managing any database. I enjoy the simplicity and security of this system. This also makes it easy to manage from my iPad, all I need is a Git client and my choice is Working Copy App. Step 1 After I installed the app on my iPad, I entered my Github details and it listed all my repos. Then, all I needed to do was selecting the repo and Clone. Step 2 Now I can edit my codes, create new files using the app. There are separate iOS IDEs that you can use, but I&apos;m fine with the WorkingCopy, plus I don&apos;t want to over-complicate the flow. Step 3 Once I&apos;m done with the code updates, I hit Commit, write my commit message and Push. That&apos;s all :) Github Pages takes care of the rest and the updates go live in less than a minute. When I need to continue on my MBP, I first do Git Pull to get the updates. The same applies to my iPad, I do Pull after making a Push from my MBP. So, both system gets the latest code and there is no conflict. BTW, the same flow works on my iPhone as well.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-codeonipad.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-codeonipad.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Emails from cheap vs expensive domains</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/emails-from-cheap-vs-expensive-domains.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emails from cheap vs expensive domains" /><published>2021-01-29T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/emails-from-cheap-vs-expensive-domains</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/emails-from-cheap-vs-expensive-domains.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early days of internet, .com was the king. It was an unconscious extension for any person. It was also an important factor to rate good at search engines. Then with the explosion of websites, finding the domain name with .com has started become a nightmare. Countless new extensions have started to come out and people have started to use Google Search more often than directly typing urls, so having a clear domain name with .com extension has become not so crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all caused an existing small problem to explode. Spams! Spammers have started to purchase cheap domain extensions and spam emails accounts with these extensions and as a response, people have started to block and assign these emails as spam. This has caused emails from these extensions to more likely fall into spams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since any online business heavily relies on email communication, you may want to reconsider the extension you are registering. There is a high chance of all your emails ending up in your visitors’ spam folder, and the only thing you can do to resolve this issue is registering a new domain name with an extension like .com, an extension that does NOT cost $1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In early days of internet, .com was the king. It was an unconscious extension for any person. It was also an important factor to rate good at search engines. Then with the explosion of websites, finding the domain name with .com has started become a nightmare. Countless new extensions have started to come out and people have started to use Google Search more often than directly typing urls, so having a clear domain name with .com extension has become not so crucial.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-cheapexpensive.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-cheapexpensive.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">If it works for you, it’s not dead</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/if-it-works-for-you-it-is-not-dead.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="If it works for you, it’s not dead" /><published>2021-01-28T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/if-it-works-for-you-it-is-not-dead</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/if-it-works-for-you-it-is-not-dead.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubyonrails.org&quot; title=&quot;Ruby on Rails&quot; targer=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; for a few years now. It&apos;s the framework enabled me to build the products I have always wanted. However whenever I research anything about RoR online, I often come across an article argues how RoR is irrelevant in recent years, how it has no future and no one should waste time with it. Here I could write a long article argues otherwise with presenting data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://trends.builtwith.com/framework&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;builtwith website research&lt;/a&gt; and all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://remoteok.io/remote-ruby-jobs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;job listings for Ruby&lt;/a&gt;, but  I’m not here to defend RoR, I want to focus on a different point.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Ruby on Rails is just a tool to build our ideas, just like what Sketch or Figma is for designers. It works for some people and doesn’t for others. Don&apos;t waste your time trying to decide what framework to use or if you should change your existing framework because of a new flashy framework. If you&apos;re productive with what you have and enjoy using it, don&apos;t distract yourself with what others are using and go with whatever works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;At the end of the day, what you build is more important than what you built it with.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;So, if it works for you, it is not dead. Use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I&apos;ve been using Ruby on Rails for a few years now. It&apos;s the framework enabled me to build the products I have always wanted. However whenever I research anything about RoR online, I often come across an article argues how RoR is irrelevant in recent years, how it has no future and no one should waste time with it. Here I could write a long article argues otherwise with presenting data from builtwith website research and all the job listings for Ruby, but  I’m not here to defend RoR, I want to focus on a different point. Ruby on Rails is just a tool to build our ideas, just like what Sketch or Figma is for designers. It works for some people and doesn’t for others. Don&apos;t waste your time trying to decide what framework to use or if you should change your existing framework because of a new flashy framework. If you&apos;re productive with what you have and enjoy using it, don&apos;t distract yourself with what others are using and go with whatever works for you. At the end of the day, what you build is more important than what you built it with. So, if it works for you, it is not dead. Use it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-itworks.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-itworks.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Beginnings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/new-beginnings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Beginnings" /><published>2021-01-27T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-27T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/new-beginnings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/new-beginnings.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s hard to believe it has been almost 8 years since my last blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed since then. I have had two kids, I read hundreds of books, I worked on tens of client projects, I experienced full time employment, I started and succeeded/failed many side projects, I have started investing in financial markets, I learned a lot and I want to start sharing it all in here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This place will be like a public journal where I pour my experiences in fatherhood, design, development, just being human in general for better or worse. I’ll post short and easy to absorb articles as I have something to share. I hope you will find something useful, inspiring...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you soon, stay safe...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It&apos;s hard to believe it has been almost 8 years since my last blog post.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-newbeginnings.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/article-newbeginnings.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>