<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-02T00:55:55+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Oykun Yilmaz</title><subtitle>Designer based in London.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Coding this blog on iPad</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/coding-this-blog-on-ipad.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coding this blog on iPad" /><published>2021-02-01T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/coding-this-blog-on-ipad</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/coding-this-blog-on-ipad.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I have been coding this simple Jekyll blog on my iPad as well as my MBP and I wanted to share my flow. This is not going to be a detailed post explaining every step in details, but an overall flow. I can get in more detailed in a separate post maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I build this website in a very simple, lightweight way by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot; title=&quot;Jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; and hosting on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com&quot; title=&quot;Github Pages&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; for free.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;This system allows me to run this blog without managing any database. I enjoy the simplicity and security of this system. This also makes it easy to manage from my iPad, all I need is a Git client and my choice is &lt;a href=&quot;https://workingcopyapp.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Working Copy App&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;mt5 mb0&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;After I installed the app on my iPad, I entered my Github details and it listed all my repos. Then, all I needed to do was selecting the repo and Clone.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;img-grey-bg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coding-on-ipad-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working copy app on iPad&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;mt5 mb0&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Now I can edit my codes, create new files in the app. There are separate iOS IDEs that you can use, but I'm fine with the WorkingCopy, plus I don't want to over-complicate the flow.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;img-grey-bg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coding-on-ipad-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working copy app on iPad&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;mt5 mb0&quot;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Once I'm done with the code updates, I hit Commit, write my commit message and Push.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coding-on-ipad-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working copy app on iPad&quot; class=&quot;center mb5&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;p class=&quot;mt5&quot;&gt;That's all :) Github Pages takes care of the rest and the updates go live in minutes if not shorter.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;When I need to continue on my MBP, I first do Git Pull to get the updates and same applies to my iPad, I do Pull after making a Push from my MBP. So both system gets the latest code and there is no conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;BTW, the same flow works on my iPhone as well.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about any steps, you can reach out to me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oykun&quot;&gt;Twitter @oykun&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have been coding this simple Jekyll blog on my iPad as well as my MBP and I wanted to share my flow. This is not going to be a detailed post explaining every step in details, but an overall flow. I can get in more detailed in a separate post maybe. I build this website in a very simple, lightweight way by using Jekyll and hosting on Github Pages for free. This system allows me to run this blog without managing any database. I enjoy the simplicity and security of this system. This also makes it easy to manage from my iPad, all I need is a Git client and my choice is Working Copy App. Step 1 After I installed the app on my iPad, I entered my Github details and it listed all my repos. Then, all I needed to do was selecting the repo and Clone. Step 2 Now I can edit my codes, create new files in the app. There are separate iOS IDEs that you can use, but I'm fine with the WorkingCopy, plus I don't want to over-complicate the flow. Step 3 Once I'm done with the code updates, I hit Commit, write my commit message and Push. That's all :) Github Pages takes care of the rest and the updates go live in minutes if not shorter. When I need to continue on my MBP, I first do Git Pull to get the updates and same applies to my iPad, I do Pull after making a Push from my MBP. So both system gets the latest code and there is no conflict. BTW, the same flow works on my iPhone as well. If you have any questions about any steps, you can reach out to me on Twitter @oykun.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/oykun.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/oykun.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Emails from cheap vs expensive domains</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/emails-from-cheap-vs-expensive-domains.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emails from cheap vs expensive domains" /><published>2021-01-29T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/emails-from-cheap-vs-expensive-domains</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/emails-from-cheap-vs-expensive-domains.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early days of internet, .com was the king. It was an unconscious extension for any person. It was also an important factor to rate good at search engines. Then with the explosion of websites, finding the domain name with .com has started become a nightmare. Countless new extensions have started to come out and people have started to use Google Search more often than directly typing urls, so having a clear domain name with .com extension has become not so crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all caused an existing small problem to explode. Spams! Spammers have started to purchase cheap domain extensions and spam emails accounts with these extensions and as a response, people have started to block and assign these emails as spam. This has caused emails from these extensions to more likely fall into spams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since any online business heavily relies on email communication, you may want to reconsider the extension you are registering. There is a high chance of all your emails ending up in your visitors’ spam folder, and the only thing you can do to resolve this issue is registering a new domain name with an extension like .com, an extension that does NOT cost $1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In early days of internet, .com was the king. It was an unconscious extension for any person. It was also an important factor to rate good at search engines. Then with the explosion of websites, finding the domain name with .com has started become a nightmare. Countless new extensions have started to come out and people have started to use Google Search more often than directly typing urls, so having a clear domain name with .com extension has become not so crucial.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">If it works for you, it’s not dead</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/if-it-works-for-you-it-is-not-dead.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="If it works for you, it’s not dead" /><published>2021-01-28T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/if-it-works-for-you-it-is-not-dead</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/if-it-works-for-you-it-is-not-dead.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I've been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubyonrails.org&quot; title=&quot;Ruby on Rails&quot; targer=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; for a few years now. It's the framework enabled me to build the products I have always wanted. However whenever I research anything about RoR online, I often come across an article argues how RoR is irrelevant in recent years, how it has no future and no one should waste time with it. Here I could write a long article argues otherwise with presenting data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://trends.builtwith.com/framework&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;builtwith website research&lt;/a&gt; and all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://remoteok.io/remote-ruby-jobs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;job listings for Ruby&lt;/a&gt;, but  I’m not here to defend RoR, I want to focus on a different point.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Ruby on Rails is just a tool to build our ideas, just like what Sketch or Figma is for designers. It works for some people and doesn’t for others. Don't waste your time trying to decide what framework to use or if you should change your existing framework because of a new flashy framework. If you're productive with what you have and enjoy using it, don't distract yourself with what others are using and go with whatever works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;At the end of the day, what you build is more important than what you built it with.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;So, if it works for you, it is not dead. Use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I've been using Ruby on Rails for a few years now. It's the framework enabled me to build the products I have always wanted. However whenever I research anything about RoR online, I often come across an article argues how RoR is irrelevant in recent years, how it has no future and no one should waste time with it. Here I could write a long article argues otherwise with presenting data from builtwith website research and all the job listings for Ruby, but  I’m not here to defend RoR, I want to focus on a different point. Ruby on Rails is just a tool to build our ideas, just like what Sketch or Figma is for designers. It works for some people and doesn’t for others. Don't waste your time trying to decide what framework to use or if you should change your existing framework because of a new flashy framework. If you're productive with what you have and enjoy using it, don't distract yourself with what others are using and go with whatever works for you. At the end of the day, what you build is more important than what you built it with. So, if it works for you, it is not dead. Use it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Beginnings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/new-beginnings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Beginnings" /><published>2021-01-27T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-27T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/new-beginnings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/new-beginnings.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to believe it has been almost 8 years since my last blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed since then. I have had two kids, I read hundreds of books, I worked on tens of client projects, I experienced full time employment, I started and succeeded/failed many side projects, I have started investing in financial markets, I learned a lot and I want to start sharing it all in here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This place will be like a public journal where I pour my experiences in fatherhood, design, development, just being human in general for better or worse. I’ll post short and easy to absorb articles as I have something to share. I hope you will find something useful, inspiring...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you soon, stay safe...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It's hard to believe it has been almost 8 years since my last blog post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-taught with Passion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2013/self-taught-with-passion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-taught with Passion" /><published>2013-05-02T01:01:01+01:00</published><updated>2013-05-02T01:01:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2013/self-taught-with-passion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2013/self-taught-with-passion.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often receive emails asking; How I became self-taught designer? If I can recommend any book, course? If I have any advise? Rather than keep replying those emails individually, I wanted to write this short post. I will be talking about design, but the things you will be reading can be applied to pretty much everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all I would like to clear a misunderstanding about the definition (in my opinion); self-taught does not (should not) mean learning without academic education. There is no university nor course that can teach you everything you need to know. Those are just tools on the path to your passion. So, whether you study at university or not, you constantly need to research, learn, practice yourself which brings the definition below in my opinion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Being self-taught is all about working hard yourself on the path of your passion with endless patience and curiosity.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few keywords here; working hard, passion, patience and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also say practising. The more you design, the more you will learn, the more confidence you will build, the better you will be and the more your vision will enlarge. You will start instantly seeing through designs and easily define what is wrong with it, what/how can be improved, and more. So, you should practise, practise and practise...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing is going to happen in a day, I have been in this industry for over 10 years and everyday I learn new things. You have to be patient and stubborn. Design the same thing again and again, and try something new in it each time. Accept this process, because this is what you are going to do for the rest of your career. Even after years of experience, you will get to that 1 beautiful final design after 99 failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always keep your eyes open, always wonder how that beautiful design you saw today is done! Why is that specific design decision given? Do not just say “it’s nice!” following with walking away but question it, dig it, research it, try to make it and make it better. Be curious about everything around you and never be satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most important matter for me. If you have the true passion, everything written above and much more is going to happen naturally, just like it has been happening for years and will be happening for good to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some extra points;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be kind:&lt;/strong&gt; We have an amazing community out there. People are willing to help each other without expecting anything back. Don’t be an arrogant asshole with world of ego, be kind, be mature, learn to accept any kind of feedback, build good relations with people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network:&lt;/strong&gt; Go to conferences, local meet-ups, be active on social media (Twitter, Facebook…), use any possible chance to meet and connect with new people. You will have fun times with them and learn a lot from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read:&lt;/strong&gt; Although I can’t recommend any specific books (there are lots, however here is few of my fav) as I’m usually asked at emails, try to read design magazines, books, blogs… Not specifically step by step design tutorials, but interviews, design terms… These are going to open your mind and eyes, help you to see the reasons of given design decisions to the objects, any kind of design all around you and it will make you appreciate more to art and designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be brave:&lt;/strong&gt; Be confident, don’t be afraid to work with people better than you, or to involve bigger projects than you have ever involved. Be brave, know that you will do more than your best and how much you will learn, how much that experience is going to add you on your path. Since the very beginning of my career, I took everything came to my path! The more projects I got involved in, the hungrier I became. I did animations with Flash, designed print catalogs, business cards, posters, application interfaces for heavy factory machines, in following years with new mobile devices I’ve designed interfaces for Android, iPhone, iPad, Mac, Windows, so on… I didn’t have any experience or education on any of those before I took these real client projects. I spent nights to learn and practise. Basically anything that came into my path, I took it, I learnt it, I enjoyed it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google:&lt;/strong&gt; Internet, the endless information source just a click away. Use it. When you don’t know how to use a software, or how to make that effect you saw, or any question in your head, just Google it! You will find videos, detailed tutorials, simple explanations. Nobody knows everything, but if you know how to find the answer, you will succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and as a last matter, never say “ok, I’m the best, I know everything!”. Remember there is always someone better than you out there. Hunt them, learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Open a design software&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Start designing that simple website or iPhone app or whatever you’ve always wanted, but keep it small.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You will have lots of questions while working on it, Google them, and move forward&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;At last you will complete it and it is awesome, your first actual design. No matter how bad it will look at the first attempt, it will be better at the next try, and even better at the further try. Keep practising...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck with your journey, believe in yourself, close your ears to people trying to break your enthusiasm, don’t give up and love what you do. You know you’ll do great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I often receive emails asking; How I became self-taught designer? If I can recommend any book, course? If I have any advise? Rather than keep replying those emails individually, I wanted to write this short post. I will be talking about design, but the things you will be reading can be applied to pretty much everything.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">White Space</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2013/white-space.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="White Space" /><published>2013-03-25T00:01:01+00:00</published><updated>2013-03-25T00:01:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2013/white-space</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2013/white-space.html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I tweeted few words about &quot;white space&quot;, it got some attention and I received emails asking more about it, so I decided to write this short post as an answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;White spaces in design are not wasted spaces. They clean the environment around the important element and gives better, easier, direct focus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-small&quot;&gt;- Oykun (@oykun) March 24, 2013&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;White space&quot; is not literally a space with white colour. It's a blank space surrounds a given element. This &quot;blank space&quot; sounds like a waste of space to some out there, which I disagree. Here is why;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/white-space-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;White space&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the example above (using same number of dots), there are lots of information (dots) to present, but one of them is the key information and it needs instant focus to give quick answer to the question; &quot;What is this thing about?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first example, as many information as possible is given in the very smallest space. You may think that you did well, because you give more in small space. Well in my opinion, it is wrong. It causes chaos, user (she) has no clue where to look, where to get the key information. So she spends seconds/minutes to make a sense of it, eventually gets frustrated and goes away. Here you lost a person who might be a potential customer or a reader or anyone else important!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the second example, white space is given to the key information in the centre. Yes, you are giving less information in the same space, but nothing wrong with it since you are giving the key information which user catches instantly without any effort. She has a clear idea about what it's telling, what it's for, now she can take instant action and explore the information given around if interested. All other dots around is making more sense to her now, because she knows the main subject from the well spaced middle dot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The middle dot could be a primary button on a remote control device, or an important line in an article, or a key visual in a poster hanged along with many others around… This is an important matter for any possible thing you can think of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/white-space-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;White space&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's look at some real life examples. Here are 2 search engines. The key element (our middle dot) is search input which user needs to be focused instantly. At the first example (Bing), it is off centred and have lots of messy elements (popups, unrelated information, heavy images, so on) around with inconsistent spacing. It is not doing terrible but still user spends minimum 5–6 seconds, and mostly likely more for unexperienced user group, to eliminate useless information around and focus on the key feature. At the second example (Google) the input is well centred with lots of white space around. The open space around gives user an instant focus to middle point. No distractions, no frustration, no time waste, it is an instant experience, it is a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today's fast moving life, every second is precious for all of us. So let's pay attention to make our products easier to use and understandable in the minimum possible time. Let's give our key information in well spaced format. Let's keep it simple and use white space efficiently. You will see the benefits in no time...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday I tweeted few words about &quot;white space&quot;, it got some attention and I received emails asking more about it, so I decided to write this short post as an answer.</summary></entry></feed>